"Side Effects of Resveratrol Supplements"
If you do have a condition
that might benefit from
resveratrol supplementation,
like diabetic foot ulcers,
or ulcerative colitis,
or menopausal pains,
and want to give resveratrol
a try,
are there any concerns,
aside from the cost,
which can exceed $10 a day?
Well, although a meta-analysis
of studies of resveratrol
found no overall effect
on LDL cholesterol levels,
a couple studies
found that resveratrol
sometimes increased LDL levels,
up to 25 percent over placebo.
As cardiovascular disease
is by far the leading killer
of diabetics,
as well as other conditions
for which you might take it,
if you do try resveratrol,
please make sure
to have your cholesterol
closely monitored.
The scientific literature
regarding resveratrol
and cardiovascular health
in general is said to be
"replete with conflicting
information and controversy."
There are no human studies
on cardiovascular disease
outcomes,
but an often-overlooked study
found that resveratrol caused
atherosclerosis in rabbits.
The study, entitled
"Resveratrol promotes
atherosclerosis
in hypercholesterolemic
rabbits,"
found that the hardening
of the arteries of bunnies
fed dietary cholesterol
was worsened by resveratrol.
But, negative or null findings
are often marginalized
by the resveratrol
research community;
so, you rarely hear about them.
Though there are
no long-term safety data,
450 milligrams a day
has been considered a safe dose,
at least in the short term,
for a 60 kilogram person
(that's like 130 pounds),
but supplementation
at higher doses
could be potentially toxic.
Daily doses of resveratrol
in excess of a gram
commonly cause mild to moderate
gastrointestinal symptoms,
such as nausea, diarrhea,
abdominal pain,
as well as "anal itchiness."
Unexpected renal toxicity
with cases
of severe kidney failure
were noted
in a five-gram-a-day study,
but this was in the context
of a cancer
that is particularly hard
on the kidneys.
Two studies, however, found
that so-called "safe" levels
of resveratrol
(at 150 to 250 milligrams a day)
may blunt
some of the positive effects
of exercise training.
In rodents, resveratrol
supplementation decreases
cardiovascular risk factors
and improves
cardiovascular function
and physical capacity.
But, when it was
put to the test in older men
(with an average age of 65),
the exact opposite was found.
Specifically,
combining resveratrol
with athletic training
abolished the reduction
in blood pressure, cholesterol,
and triglycerides
normally associated
with exercise,
had a more artery-constricting
effect than a dilating one,
and led to a significantly
lower increase
in aerobic fitness.
Rodents on resveratrol get
enhanced exercise performance,
but, in people,
the resveratrol induced
a 45 percent lower increase
in maximum aerobic capacity
compared with those
taking a sugar pill.
For all their working out,
the resveratrol
was undercutting their efforts.
An apparent impairment
in peak aerobic power
was also noted in young men
following high-intensity
interval training
on resveratrol
compared to placebo.
A recent review
overreacted to these data
by suggesting "foods
containing resveratrol
should not be consumed
during exercise,"
but to even reach
the lower dose of 150 milligrams
you'd have to eat
more than like
a hundred pounds
of grapes a day.
Though, I suppose
if you did manage to stuff
in a hundred pounds of grapes,
it might, indeed,
be a little impairing.
The exercise impairment
with resveratrol supplements
does make sense, though,
given its purported mechanism.
Sirtuin activation
by resveratrol
is thought to occur
via the activation
of the body's fuel gauge, AMPK,
by interfering
with energy production
in the mitochondria powerplants
in our cells.
Mouse cells react by increasing
mitochondria to compensate,
but human cells
apparently do not;
so, the energy-dimming effect
of resveratrol
may explain why the effects
of exercise are impaired.
What works in animals may not
necessarily work in people.
Thus, concluded one review,
the hype regarding resveratrol
may "turn out to be
nothing more
than a sleight-of-hand
marketing device
using peer-reviewed, published,
non-human research
as a cover."
Although some like Dr. Oz
have recommended resveratrol
as a life-extending
"miracle molecule,"
given that evidence-based
responses
are sparse-and-controversial
such "claims, innuendo,
and hyperbole"
are said to be "atrocious."
The fitness-blunting exercise
study of older adults
was supported in part
by a manufacturer
of resveratrol supplements.
To their credit,
the researchers responded
to an angry letter from
a supplement company consultant
that "it is our opinion
that we, as scientists,
have a responsibility
to report what we find
and not to twist our findings
to fit
the commercial interests."